<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc
  SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
          <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<rfc ipr='trust200902'
     docName='draft-shore-icmp-aup-00'>

<front>
  <title abbrev='ICMP AUP'>
    An Acceptable Use Policy for New ICMP Types and Codes
  </title>

  <author initials='M.' surname='Shore' fullname='Melinda Shore'>
    <organization>No Mountain Software</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>PO Box 16271</street>
        <city>Two Rivers</city>
        <region>AK</region>
        <code>99716</code>
        <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1 907 322 9522</phone>
      <email>melinda.shore@nomountain.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials='C.' surname='Pignataro' fullname='Carlos Pignataro'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
        <region>NC</region>
        <code>27709</code>
        <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <email>cpignata@cisc.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date month='July' year='2012' />

  <area>Operations</area>

  <abstract>
    <t>Some recent proposals to add new Internet Control Message
      Protocol (ICMP) types and/or codes
      have highlighted a need to describe policies for when adding
      new features to ICMP is desirable and when it is not.  In
      this document we provide a basic description of ICMP's
      role in the IP stack and some guidelines for the future.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section title='Introduction'>
    <t>There have been some recent proposals to add new message
      types and codes to <xref target='RFC792'>ICMP</xref> (see,
      for example, <xref target='templin' />).  Not all
      of these proposal are consistent with the design and intent
      of ICMP, and so we attempt to lay out a description of when
      (and when not) to move functionality into ICMP.</t>

    <t>This document is the result of discussions within the
      IETF Operations area "ICMP Society," and concerns expressed
      by the OPS area leadership.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="ICMP's role in the internet">
    <t>ICMP was originally intended to be a mechanism for routers
      to report error conditions back to hosts <xref target='RFC792' />.
      The word "control" in the protocol name did not describe
      ICMP's function (i.e. it did not "control" the internet), but
      rather that it was used to communicate about the control
      functions in the internet.  For example, even though ICMP
      included a redirect message type, it was and is not used as a
      routing protocol.</t>

    <t>Most likely because of the presence of the word
      "control" in the protocol name, ICMP is often
      understood to be a control protocol, borrowing some
      terminology from circuit networks and the PSTN.  That
      is probably not correct - it might be more correct to
      describe it as being closer to a management plane
      protocol, given the data plane/control plane/
      management plane taxonomy often used in describing
      telephony protocols.  However, layering in IP networks
      is not very clean and there's often some intermingling
      of function that can tend to lead to confusion about
      where to place new functions.</t>

    <t>This document provides some background on the differences
      between control and management traffic, and finishes by
      proposing that any future additional ICMP types or codes
      be limited to what in telephony networks would be
      considered management plane traffic.</t>

  </section>

  <section title='Management vs control'>
    <t>In this section we attempt to draw a distinction
      between management and control planes, acknowledging
      in advance that this may serve to muddle the
      differences even further.  Ultimately the difference
      may not matter that much for the purpose of creating a
      policy for adding new types to ICMP, but because that
      terminology has become ubiquitous, even in IETF
      discussions, and because it has come up in prior
      discussions of ICMP policies, it seems worthwhile
      to take a few paragraph to describe what they are
      and what they are not.</t>

    <t>The terms "management plane" and "control plane"
      came into use to describe one aspect of layering in
      telecommunications networks.  It is particularly
      important, in the context of this discussion, to understand
      that "control plane" in telecomm networks almost always
      refers to 'signaling,' or call control and network
      control information.  This includes "call"
      establishment and teardown, route establishment and
      teardown, requesting QoS or other parameters, and so
      on.  </t>

    <t>"Management," on the other hand, tends to fall under the
      rubric "OAM," or "Operations, Administration, and Management."
      typical functions include fault management and performance
      monitoring (Service Level Agreement [SLA] compliance),
      discovery, etc.</t>

  </section> <!-- management vs control -->

  <section title='Where ICMP fits'>
    <t>The correct answer to the question of where ICMP fits into
      the management/control/data taxonomy is that it doesn't,
      at least not neatly.  While some of the message types
      are unambiguously management message (ICMP type 3, or
      "unreachable" messages), others are less clearly
      identifiable.  For example, the "redirect" (ICMP type 5)
      message can be construed to contain control (in this
      case, routing) information, even though it is in some
      very real sense an error message.</t>

    <t>At this time,
      <list style='symbols'>
        <t>there are many, many other protocols that can be (and
          are) used for control traffic, whether they're routing
          protocols, telephony signaling protocols, QoS protocols,
          middlebox protocols, AAA protocols, etc.</t>
        <t>the transport characteristics needed by control traffic
          can be incompatible with the ICMP protocol standard --
          for example, they may require reliable delivery, very
          large payloads, or have security requirements that cannot
          be met.</t>
      </list>
      and because of thiswe propose that any future message
      types added to ICMP must stay within the "management
      plane" domain, and in particular that it would not be
      appropriate or desirable for control (or signaling)
      messages to be conveyed by ICMP.</t>
  </section>
    
  <section title='Security considerations'>
    <t>This document attempts to describe a high-level policy
      for adding ICMP types and codes.  While special attention
      must be paid to the security implications of any particular
      new ICMP type or code, specific security considerations
      are outside the scope of this paper.</t>
  </section> <!-- security considerations -->

  <section title='IANA considerations'>
    <t>There are no actions required by IANA.</t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>
  <references title='Informative references'>
    <reference anchor="RFC792">
      <front>
        <title>INTERNET CONTROL MESSAGE PROTOCOL</title>
        <author initials="J" surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
          <organization>ISI</organization>
        </author>
        <date month="September" year="1981" />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="792" />
    </reference>
   
<reference anchor='templin'>
<front>
<title>Asymmetric Extended Route Optimization (AERO)</title>

<author initials='F' surname='Templin' fullname='Fred Templin'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='18' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>Nodes attached to common multi-access link types (e.g., multicast- capable, shared media, non-broadcast multiple access (NBMA), etc.) can exchange packets as neighbors on the link, but may not always be provisioned with sufficient routing information for optimal neighbor selection.  Such nodes should therefore be able to discover a trusted intermediate router on the link that provides both forwarding services to reach off-link destinations and redirection services to inform the node of an on-link neighbor that is closer to the final destination.  This redirection can provide a useful route optimization, since the triangular path from the ingress link neighbor, to the intermediate router, and finally to the egress link neighbor may be considerably longer than the direct path from ingress to egress.  However, ordinary redirection may lead to operational issues on certain link types and/or in certain deployment scenarios. This document therefore introduces an Asymmetric Extended Route Optimization (AERO) capability that addresses the issues.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-templin-aero-08' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-templin-aero-08.txt' />
</reference>


  </references>
</back>
</rfc>
